Register of the Susan Louise Dyer papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Susan Louise Dyer papers
1874-1966
60023
Hoover Institution Archives
8 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes, 1 oversize folder, 10 envelopes, 1 phonotape, memorabilia (4.2 linear feet)
The Susan Louise Dyer papers contain materials that reflect Dyer's personal ties to Herbert and Lou Henry Hoover, her association with Stanford University, and her service with the American Red Cross and the Girl Scouts of the United States. The papers largely consist of correspondence, clippings, diaries, photographs, and printed matter.
Dyer, Susan Louise, 1877-1966.
Arrangement note
The collection is organized into 10 series: Biographical file; Correspondence; Writings; Subject file; Printed matter; Small memorabilia; Photographs; Photo file; Oversize materials; and Large memorabilia
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1960.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the library catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
1877 Born, Ottawa, Illinois
1899 Awarded bachelor's degree, Stanford University
1901 Awarded master's degree, Stanford University
1901-1918 Biology teacher, Alameda High School, Alameda, California
1918-1919 Served with American Red Cross in France and Germany
1925-1926 Head of Education Department, Girl Scouts of America, New York City
1932 Chairwoman, Women's Hoover for President Club, Palo Alto, California
1966 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
The Susan Louise Dyer papers contain materials that reflect Dyer's personal ties to Herbert and Lou Henry Hoover, her association with Stanford University, and her service with the American Red Cross and the Girl Scouts of the United States. The papers largely consist of correspondence, clippings (arranged in an extensive subject file), diaries, photographs, and printed matter.
Dyer became friends with Lou Henry Hoover while both were students at Stanford University. While at Stanford, Dyer also met Herbert Hoover, and she remained close to both Hoovers during their lifetimes. The papers contain correspondence with Herbert and Lou Henry Hoover, as well as numerous clippings (in the Subject file series) about Herbert Hoover's political career and his many activities after leaving the presidency. Dyer's friendship with the Hoovers was the focus of an extensive oral history interview conducted with her in 1966; a transcript of this interview can be found in the Biographical file of the papers. Additionally, there are short entries in Dyer's diaries (also found in the Biographical file) that record her visits to the White House during the Hoover administration.
Dyer's work with the American Red Cross in France and Germany after World War I is described in detail in the many letters she wrote at the time to Louise P. Fullerton, copies of which can be found in the Correspondence series of the papers. This series also contains Dyer's correspondence with Ray Lyman Wilbur, president of Stanford University, as well as with officials of the Hoover Institution. This correspondence largely relates to Dyer's involvement with fundraising activities on behalf of the university and the Hoover Library. There are also a number of monographs and pamphlets published by Stanford University in the printed matter series of the papers.
The papers also contain Dyer's correspondence with officials of the Girl Scouts of the United States, an organization with which she was associated for many years.
American National Red Cross.; Girl Scouts.; Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; Hoover, Lou Henry, 1874-1944.; Stanford University.; International relief.; World War, 1914-1918--War work.
- Biographical file, 1888-1966
  - Address book, 1960 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Calendar, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Certificates, 1917-1965 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Clippings, 1894-1966 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Curriculum vitae, 1940 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Diaries, 1888-1937
    - 1888 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - 1894-1895 (Box-folder 1: 7)
    - 1896 (Box-folder 1: 8)
    - 1913 (Box-folder 1: 9)
    - 1928-1932 (Box-folder 1: 10)
    - 1929-1930 (Box-folder 1: 11)
    - 1933-1937 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Invitations, 1895-1962
    - 1895-1932 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - 1941-1962 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Map used on trip taken with Lou Henry Hoover, 1941 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Passports, 1918-1931 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Programs, 1895-1960
    - 1895-1929 (Box-folder 2: 6)
    - 1930-1931 (Box-folder 2: 7)
    - 1941-1960 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - School records, 1896 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Transcript of oral history interview, 1966 (Box-folder 2: 10)
- Correspondence, 1911-1966
  - Unidentified, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Alameda City Schools, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - American Red Cross, 1918-1920 (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Bishop, Claire Huchet, 1944 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - Bowman, G. L., 1944 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - Campbell, Mildred Hall, 1933-1964 (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - Committee for the Dedication of the Hoover Library, 1940 (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - Crumpton, Helen, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 2: 18)
  - Decourt, Marguerite, 1920 (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - Fesler, Ruth, 1928 (Box-folder 2: 20)
  - Fullerton, Louise P., 1918-1919 (Box-folder 3: 1-2)
  - Fullerton, William D., 1918-1919 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Girl Scouts of the United States of America, 1965 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Henle, Raymond, 1966 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Hicks, John D., 1960-1961 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Hoover, Herbert, 1942-1964 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Hoover, Lou Henry, 1920-1941 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Hoover, Margaret Coberly, 1962 (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - Hoover family, 1911-1940 (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - Hoover Institution, 1965 (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - Kendrick, Kathryn, 1944 (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - Klein, J. J., 1966 (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - Loesch, May B., 1930 (Box-folder 3: 14)
  - Miller, Bernice, 1961 (Box-folder 3: 15)
  - Rickard, Edgar, 1944 (Box-folder 3: 16)
  - Santa Clara County Girl Scout Council, 1966 (Box-folder 3: 17)
  - Stanford University, 1928-1966 (Box-folder 3: 18)
  - Stanford Women's Relief Unit, 1918 (Box-folder 3: 19)
  - Taylor, Myron, 1931 (Box-folder 3: 20)
  - Wickett, F. A., 1949 (Box-folder 3: 21)
  - White, Howard P., 1919 (Box-folder 3: 22)
  - Wilbur, Ray Lyman, 1940-1947 (Box-folder 3: 23)
  - Witcofski, Christina, 1944-1964 (Box-folder 3: 24)
- Writings, 1901-1964
  - "Studies on the Central Nervous System of Bdellostoma Stouti Lock.", 1901 (Box-folder 3: 25)
  - "The Friends of Music at Stanford", 1958 (Box-folder 3: 26)
  - Notes on Herbert Hoover and the Hoover family, 1964 (Box-folder 3: 27)
- Subject file, 1899-1966
  - American Red Cross, 1919 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Democratic Party, 1932-1933 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Dyer family, 1889-1910 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Eisenhower, Mamie, 1958 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Fields, Alonzo, 1960 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Girl Scouts of the United States of America, 1944 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Herbert Hoover Presidential Library, 1962-1965 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Hoover, Herbert, 1928-1965
    - 1928 (Box-folder 4: 8-10)
    - 1929 (Box-folder 4: 11-12)
    - 1930 (Box-folder 4: 13)
    - 1931 (Box-folder 4: 14)
    - 1932 (Box-folder 4: 15-17)
    - 1933-1934 (Box-folder 4: 18)
    - 1936-1937 (Box-folder 4: 19)
    - 1939-1940 (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - 1941 (Box-folder 5: 2-3)
    - 1942-1943 (Box-folder 5: 4)
    - 1944-1945 (Box-folder 5: 5)
    - 1946-1949 (Box-folder 5: 6)
    - 1951-1953 (Box-folder 5: 7)
    - 1954-1955 (Box-folder 5: 8)
    - 1956 (Box-folder 5: 9)
    - 1957 (Box-folder 5: 10)
    - 1958-1959 (Box-folder 5: 11)
    - 1960 (Box-folder 5: 12)
    - 1961 (Box-folder 5: 13)
    - 1962-1963 (Box-folder 5: 14)
    - 1964 (Box-folder 5: 15-16)
    - 1965 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Hoover, Herbert, Jr., 1954-1962 (Box-folder 6: 2)
  - Hoover, Lou Henry, 1944-1962 (Box-folder 6: 3)
  - Hoover, Margaret Coberly, 1958 (Box-folder 6: 4)
  - Hoover Institution, 1958-1966 (Box-folder 6: 5)
  - Kappa Kappa Gamma, 1897-1963 (Box-folder 6: 6)
  - Pedlow, James A., 1921 (Box-folder 6: 7)
  - Roosevelt, Theodore, 1919 (Box-folder 6: 8)
  - Stanford, Leland, 1893 (Box-folder 6: 9)
  - Stanford University, 1895-1966
    - 1895-1901 (Box-folder 6: 10)
    - 1941 (Box-folder 6: 11)
    - 1949-1955 (Box-folder 6: 12)
    - 1960-1962 (Box-folder 6: 13)
    - 1964 (Box-folder 6: 14)
    - 1965-1966 (Box-folder 6: 15)
  - United States Army, 1919 (Box-folder 6: 16)
  - Wilbur, Ray Lyman, 1949 (Box-folder 6: 17)
  - Wilson, Woodrow, 1917 (Box-folder 6: 18)
  - World War II, 1939 (Box-folder 6: 19)
  - Young Women's Christian Association, 1962 (Box-folder 6: 20)
- Printed matter, 1903-1966
  - Monographs, 1903-1942
    - 1903 (Box-folder 7: 1)
    - 1919 (Box-folder 7: 2-3)
    - 1927 (Box-folder 7: 4)
    - 1941 (Box-folder 7: 5)
    - 1942 (Box-folder 7: 6)
  - Pamphlets, 1921-1966
    - 1921-1925 (Box-folder 7: 7)
    - 1939-1951 (Box-folder 7: 8)
    - 1957-1966 (Box-folder 7: 9)
  - Serial issues, 1957-1966
    - 1957 (Box-folder 7: 10)
    - 1965-1966 (Box-folder 7: 11)
- Small memorabilia, 1899-1932
  - American flags, 1918 (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - Campaign buttons and ribbon, 1928-1932 (Box-folder 8: 2)
  - Diploma covers, 1899-1901 (Box-folder 8: 3)
  - Embroidered insignias for American Red Cross unit, 1918 (Box-folder 8: 4)
  - Letter opener, 1920 (Box-folder 8: 5)
- Photographs (arranged in 2013), 1885-1966
  - One print depicting Susan L. Dyer and elementary school classmates, 1885 (Box-folder 8: 6)
  - Two prints depicting Susan L. Dyer, 1896-1899 (Box-folder 8: 7)
  - Five prints depicting Susan L. Dyer and friends, 1902-1910 (Box-folder 8: 8)
  - Nine prints depicting Susan L. Dyer, 1918 (Box-folder 8: 9)
  - Four prints depicting Susan L. Dyer and American Red Cross personnel in France, 1918 (Box-folder 8: 10)
  - Two prints depicting Susan L. Dyer and Eva Sorensen, 1919 (Box-folder 8: 11)
  - Six prints depicting Susan L. Dyer, Bush Fullerton, and others in Germany, 1919 (Box-folder 8: 12)
  - Two prints depicting Susan L. Dyer, 1928-1932 (Box-folder 8: 13)
  - One print depicting Susan L. Dyer, 1950 (Box-folder 8: 14)
  - One print depicting Susan L. Dyer and fellow Stanford alumni, 1959 (Box-folder 8: 15)
  - One print depicting Susan L. Dyer and Raymond Henle, 1966 (Box-folder 8: 16)
  - Two prints depicting Lou Henry Hoover, 1898 (Box-folder 8: 17)
  - One print depicting Lou Henry Hoover, 1900 (Box-folder 8: 18)
  - Eleven prints depicting Herbert Hoover and others at a motorcade in Palo Alto, California, 1928 (Box-folder 8: 19)
  - One print depicting the unveiling of a portrait of Lou Henry Hoover, 1955 (Box-folder 8: 20)
  - Four prints depicting Bush Fullerton, 1919 (Box-folder 8: 21)
  - Two prints depicting Madame Melein, 1922 (Box-folder 8: 22)
  - Two prints depicting the home of Susan L. Dyer in Alameda, California, 1918 (Box-folder 8: 23)
  - Two prints depicting a captured German tank near Rheims, France, 1918 (Box-folder 8: 24)
  - Twenty one prints depicting scenes in France and Germany, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 8: 25)
  - Fourteen prints depicting American Red Cross personnel in Germany, 1919 (Box-folder 8: 26)
  - One print depicting elementary schoolchildren, 1889 (Box-folder 8: 27)
  - Twelve prints depicting French war orphans, 1919 (Box-folder 8: 28)
  - Two prints depicting the Hoover Library, 1945 (Box-folder 8: 29)
  - One print depicting Hoover Tower, 1960 (Box-folder 8: 30)
- Photo file (photographs separated prior to 2013), 1874-1960
  - One print depicting Wallace Sterling and one print depicting Reuben Head, 1940-1960 (Envelope A)
  - Seven prints depicting Lou Henry Hoover and four illustrations of scenes in Arizona, 1874-1941 (Envelope B)
  - Twenty prints depicting Lou Henry Hoover, Herbert Hoover, and various members of the Hoover family, 1897-1954 (Envelope C)
  - Six prints depicting Lou Henry Hoover, 1898-1931 (Envelope D)
  - One print depicting Susan L. Dyer, one print depicting Clara Guenough, and one print depicting Kathy Bingham, 1897-1951 (Envelope E)
  - One print depicting Peggy Ann, Peter, and Joan Hoover; and two prints depicting reunions of the Stanford class of 1899, 1930-1936 (Envelope F)
  - Four prints depicting Herbert Hoover and Lou Henry Hoover, 1918-1932 (Envelope G)
  - Seven prints depicting Lou Henry Hoover and one print depicting Herbert Hoover and Lou Henry Hoover, 1931-1932 (Envelope H)
  - Six prints depicting Lou Henry Hoover; one print depicting Lou Henry Hoover and Peggy Ann Hoover; one print depicting David Starr Jordan; one print depicting S. R. Lewis; two prints depicting Hoover Tower, 1920-1950 (Envelope mI)
  - Sixteen lithographs depicting scenes in Washington, D.C., France, and Germany; and one watercolor painting of a child, 1918-1937 (Envelope mJ)
- Oversize materials, 1904-1961
  - One album of photographs depicting scenes of Stanford University, 1904 (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - One album of clippings and photographs relating to Susan L. Dyer's service in the American Red Cross, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 9: 2)
  - One album of clippings relating to Herbert Hoover, 1930-1961 (Box 10)
    Scope and Contents note
    Items previously located in Box/Folder 9: 3.
- Large memorabilia, 1920-1940
  - Large handbell, small handbell, and candle holder, 1920 (Memorabilia-cabinet 26)
  - Small statue of Buddha, 1940 (Memorabilia-cabinet 26a)
  - Stand for statue of Buddha, 1940 (Memorabilia-cabinet 26b)